♪ ♪
( rain pattering )
( Crowd shouting and chanting in German )
( Shouting and chanting continue )
( Clattering )
( Loud banging , clattering )
( Distant siren , whistles blowing )
♪ ' cause I 'll be leaving in the .. ♪
( doorbell ringing )
- ♪ in the fairest ♪ - ( Knocking )
♪ of the seasons ♪
( knocking continues )
Man : Oh .
Patricia .
♪ That I 'll be leaving ♪
♪ in the fairest of the seasons ♪
♪ do I stay or should I go ? ♪
So , I have a patient that is coming in five minutes .
I can ask him to come back later .
Please .
( Patricia chuckles )
♪ ' cause I 'll be leaving ♪
♪ in the fairest of the seasons ♪
( continues singing indistinctly )
♪ that I 'll be leaving ♪
♪ in the ... ♪
this song , it 's stuck in my head , and it 's so loud .
They 're going to try to keep her alive after all .
Markos ?
( Patricia panting quietly )
( Loud bang outside , crowd shouting )
( Crowd chanting in German )
I have to tell Sara to get out of there .
She 's the only girl I actually give a damn about .
( Curtains closing )
Patricia : If I leave without her ,
they may pick her next .
Or Olga .
I should warn Olga , too .
Olga 's already figured out things .
She saw how they groomed me . ( Chuckles )
There 's more in that building than what you can see .
( Patricia panting quietly )
They 've been underground since the war .
And you think they can hear you now ?
( Eerie voices whispering indistinctly )
At the beginning , they gave me things .
Perfect balance , perfect sleep .
Talking with our minds .
But they took my hair .
They took my urine . They ...
They took my eyes .
Now she can see me .
♪ ' cause I 'll be leaving ♪
♪ in the fairest of the seasons ♪
♪ I 'll be leaving ... ♪
Patricia : Mother Markos .
Oh , she wants to get inside of me .
I can feel her .
Oh , I thought I wanted it .
( Sighs )
I let it happen .
( Eerie voices laughing )
( Gasping )
( Eerie voices laughing , moaning )
( Grunting , panting )
( Whimpers softly )
If they find out I was here , they won 't hesitate .
( Door opens )
( Patricia gasps , pants )
( Door opens and closes )
( Speaking German )
( Bird squawking )
♪ ♪
- ( Wheezing quietly ) - ( Indistinct whispering )
( Water splashing gently )
( Wheezing continues )
♪ this is what I was thinking ♪
( quiet , indistinct chatter )
♪ about our bodies ♪
( crying )
♪ what they mean ♪
♪ for our salvation ♪
( objects clattering quietly )
♪ only the clothes that ♪
♪ we stand up in ♪
♪ just the ground ♪
♪ on which we stand ♪
( banging , creaking )
♪ is the darkness ♪
♪ ours to take ? ♪
Okay , that 's good . That 's good .
♪ Bathed in lightning ♪
♪ bathed in heat ♪
( Takes deep breath )
( Wheezing continues )
♪ all is well I
♪ as long as we keep spinning ♪
♪ here now ♪
♪ dancing behind the wall
♪ hear the old songs ♪
♪ and laughter within ♪
( wheezing continues )
♪ when I arrive , will ♪
- morning , pastor . - ♪ you come and find me ? ♪
Did the rain get your clothes all wet ?
No , don 't you worry . The girls just hung that all up .
- ♪ in a crowd ♪ - Two days of rain
is what I just heard on the radio .
- That 'll just about do it . - Just about .
♪ Be one of them ♪
- ( door opens and closes ) - Pastor : How is she today ?
- mother wants us ♪ - Man : Much the same .
♪ Right beside her ♪
♪ no tomorrows ♪
♪ at peace . ♪
( wheezing continues )
( Wheezing continues )
( Wheezing fades )
( Announcement in German over pa . )
( Chatter in German )
( Train screeching in distance )
( Train rumbling and screeching )
( Quiet chatter )
( Objects rattling and banging )
( Distant banging )
( Panting )
( Woman speaking German )
You 're miss Tanner ?
Yes . Come in .
( Panting quietly )
Tanner : Nah ?
I tried to call you at your hotel this morning
to ask you if you could reschedule .
- Why ? - Company business .
It 's not a good time just today .
But here you are .
( Sighs )
( Taking deep breaths )
( Continues breathing deeply )
Woman : And one , and two ,
and three , and four ,
and five ,
and six , and seven ,
and eight .
Elbows up . And one ...
Come in , Susie .
( Susie clears throat quietly )
Miss Millius and miss Mandel are the company 's repetiteurs .
Susie : And Veva Blanc ?
I was told she would be here .
( Chuckling ) : Oh , dear .
You have no formal training or references .
Your insistence to audition
happened to catch madame Blanc on a good day .
But you really shouldn 't be here at all .
Do you understand ?
Mm-hmm . Yeah ?
Good .
( Speaks German )
Uh ...
I prefer dancing without music .
- Danke schoen . - ( Laughing )
You can keep time in your head , yes ?
( Clears throat quietly )
( Sighs )
( Lights buzz quietly )
( Gasps )
Mm-hmm , and hypnose .
And here we have ...
A line between the elbows .
Face forward .
Perfect , and ... morphus .
And here , not so close to the face .
More like you 're holding a bird or something .
( Inhales sharply )
( Panting )
( Panting heavily )
♪ ♪
( heavy panting continues )
( Panting continues in distance )
( Heavy , rapid panting )
♪ ♪
( panting )
( Indistinct chatter )
Woman : They did it when we were in morning rehearsal .
They just put her things in shipping boxes .
Woman 2 : You don 't think she had to go underground , do you ?
Woman 1 : I don 't care what happened .
I just want her to call .
I 'm really worried .
Woman : Fraulein Bannion .
Kommen sie .
I 've just spoken with madame Blanc .
Well done , miss Bannion .
( Susie laughs )
I imagine you will need to return home
to settle things and make arrangements
for moving to Berlin .
No . No , no .
I can start right now . ( Chuckles )
Good .
This is miss Boutaher ,
our technical director .
Guten tag .
And this is miss Vendegast .
- She acts as house mother ... - Hello .
For our dancers who reside here .
Where 'd you come from ?
( Clears throat )
Ohio .
( Chuckling )
We operate as a sort of Ruth bré collective .
As we cannot pay our dancers a lot of money ,
we offer dormitory-style rooms , rent-free .
You don 't ... you don 't charge anything at all ?
Not a Mark .
( Chuckles )
In this company , we fully understand
the importance of a woman 's financial autonomy .
( Chuckles )
Normally , it would be full at this time of year ,
but we have had a room open .
Yeah . Patricia 's .
Do you know Patricia ?
Susie : Mmm
no , I heard some girls talking
about her in the hall .
- Ah . - ( Distant door closes )
Now that you 're one of us , I won 't be coy .
Patricia has just left the company
under sad circumstances .
We think she won 't be back , so there 's room if you want .
We 'll send you one of our girls to help you with your luggage .
After lunch .
It 's all right for you ?
Yes .
It 's-it ... it 's all ...
- Yes . - ( Laughter )
It 's perfect .
( Chuckling )
- ( Thunder crashes ) - ( Knocking at door )
Hello . Hi . I 'm sorry I 'm late .
- Hi . - It 's the rain .
Whenever it rains in Berlin , everyone jumps in a cab ,
and like an idiot , I just let ours go .
Hi . I 'm Sara .
We 're gonna have to take our chances on the street .
Do you have an umbrella ?
Oh , when you weren 't here by 6 : 00 ,
I had to take the room for another night .
Oh . God , Susie , I 'm sorry .
Everything was a mess at the company today .
- ( Chuckles ) - Why are you smiling ?
- I 'm sor ... I-I ... - ( Indistinct chatter )
Um , uh , when you said Berlin a second ago ,
you said " everyone in Berlin , "
and I just thought that ... That includes me now .
I live in Berlin .
- Yes . Congrats . - ( Chuckles )
I heard you were a sensation today .
Have you called your family yet , to tell them ?
Miss Blanc came into my audition .
But she left right after .
( Chuckles ) She 's incredible .
The way she transmits her work , her energy .
When it shines on you , it 's ...
" Addictive " is the word for it .
She 's tough .
She kept the company alive through the war .
When the reich just wanted women to shut off their minds
and keep their uteruses open ,
there was Blanc .
Thank you .
La vraie chose . ( The real thing )
What ?
W-was that French ?
( Loud bang , rattling )
( Alarm ringing in distance )
( Indistinct shouting in distance )
Sara : It 's a bomb .
I can smell it .
There 's a bank that way .
Don 't you know what 's happening here ?
The hijackers are negotiating a release
of the Stammheim prisoners tonight .
The RAF .
Baader-Meinhof .
They kidnapped an executive .
During the war , he was a Nazi SS , an officer .
Now he runs the German employers ' association .
You don 't get how awful that is , do you ?
( Upbeat music playing over radio )
( Music stops )
( Indistinct chatter over radio )
Sorry .
I 'm just worried about my friend .
( Alarm ringing )
( Panting quietly )
( Vendegast humming a tune )
( Continues humming )
( Door opens , closes )
♪ ♪
( quiet , indistinct chatter )
( Radio broadcast continues )
( Indistinct chatter )
( Panting )
( Chatter in German )
( Chatter continues )
( Train whirring and rattling )
( Chatter )
( Buzzing )
( Buzzing stops , door opens )
♪ ♪
( inhales deeply )
( Quiet chatter )
♪ ♪
( keys jingling )
( Birds squawking and tweeting )
( Takes deep breath )
Sara : Bedrooms are on the second floor .
( Indistinct chatter and laughter )
( Music playing over radio )
( Sighs )
Why don 't you try speaking to me like you love me ?
Huh ?
For a change .
( Sighs )
This is my room .
And here ...
Is yours .
We 're neighbours .
You can knock on the wall if you ever need anything .
( Chatter and laughter continue in other rooms )
( Grunts quietly )
( TV broadcast playing in German )
( Door opens and closes )
Blanc : Good morning .
- Good morning . - Hello .
- Good morning . - Good morning .
- Hi . - Good morning . Good morning .
How 's your knee ? Okay ?
It 's wonderful you 're here .
- Thank you . - ( Quiet chatter )
We have some happier company business today .
We have a new dancer .
This is Susie Bannion , who 's joining us from America .
I was privileged to witness her audition yesterday .
We are very lucky to have her .
Would you like to say something , Susie ?
Um ...
I don 't know .
Hello .
( Quiet laughter )
I feel like I 'm not even here yet .
I don 't know .
You join in whenever you feel ready ,
but there 's no rush .
Welcome to our little family .
I 'm Susie .
- Hi . Hi . - ( Indistinct chatter )
All right , so for today 's rehearsal ,
I want to pick up exactly where we left off with volk .
I 've spoken to Olga ,
and she 's going to dance Patricia 's part .
And , Sara , I 'd like you to dance Olga 's part .
Is everyone happy with that ?
- ( Quiet murmurs of agreement ) - Okay .
Good .
( Mid-tempo piano music playing )
No , no , no , no , no , no , no , no . Music off , please .
- One moment . - ( Music stops )
Okay , so ...
And one , and two , and three .
You pull it from the ground .
All right ? Gravity , remember .
And everybody from here , please .
And Tanner .
One and two and three .
And one , and two , and three .
Und eins , und zwei , und drei .
- Und eins , und zwei , und drei . - ( Dancers panting )
This is shit .
- Such shit . - Okay .
Why don 't we all break for ten minutes .
You can 't even be bothered to respect your own lies .
Miss Ivanova !
Blanc : No , no , no , no , no , it 's okay .
Let 's face this .
Patricia is gone , Olga .
We don 't know where .
If she 's gone into hiding , she wouldn 't have told us ,
would she ? She would have told someone .
We know that she had dealings
with people who are interested in targets .
And we know there was another bomb
in Kreuzberg last night .
Olga : She wouldn 't do that .
( Blanc shushing )
She wanted to live her beliefs .
Who doesn 't admire that ?
And there 's so much to change in the world .
If she wants to live in a cellar
filling bottles with petrol , that 's her choice .
And who won 't be heartbroken if she 's shot by police ?
( Sobbing ) : You manipulate everything .
She didn 't trust you because you 're hypocrites .
Will you take Olga to her room , please , Tanner ?
( Olga crying )
No , miss Tanner !
Call Olga a cab .
She 's had enough .
And is going to pack her things
and get the fuck out from this box of rabies !
( Olga sobbing )
( Tanner laughing )
Blanc : I 'm sorry about that .
It 's a hot thing we do .
Okay , so ... who will dance the protagonist ?
Sonia ?
I can 't . Not yet .
Caroline ?
Very well . We 'll manage .
I suggest that we all take it from the top .
Susie : I 'll dance .
I know it .
It 's in the documentary .
I-I 've seen it a hundred times at the library .
Sweetheart , we rehearsed this piece
for ten months before we performed it .
I 've seen it in person , too .
Tanner : First do it alone , then .
We don 't want to put the others at risk .
The last thing we need
is someone to get kicked in the ribs .
( Chuckles quietly )
All right ?
♪ ♪
( Mid-tempo piano music plays )
( Takes deep breath )
( Panting )
Okay , stop . Stop , stop .
- Stop . - ( Music stops )
All right .
Clear your head .
I want you to start over .
Have you stretched ?
This is no joke .
♪ ♪
( quiet chatter in German )
( Distant laughter )
- ( Door opens ) - ( Laughter continues )
- ( Laughter stops ) - Olga .
( Muffled , distorted whooshing )
( Muffled , distorted whispering )
- ( Whooshing , whispering stop ) - ( Laughter resumes )
( Sighs , grunts )
( Laughter continues )
( Exhales )
( Sniffs , grunts )
( Laughter echoing )
( Exhales , sniffs )
( Grunting , sniffing )
( Laughter echoing )
( Panting )
Woman : Olga .
( Speaking German )
Come .
( Whimpers , sobs )
( Sobbing , speaking indistinctly )
Blanc : Remember , you start on one with the music ,
and if you feel ill at any time , just stop .
You start here .
And ...
( Piano music plays )
( Rhythmic breathing )
( Groans )
( Gasps , coughs )
( Exhales sharply )
( Pained gasping )
( Panting rhythmically )
( Grunts )
( Yells , coughs )
( Gasps , grunts )
( Pained grunt )
( Grunts )
- ( Crunching ) - ( Gasps , screams )
( Pained gasping )
( Panting )
( Coughs , wheezes )
Lauter !
( Music volume increases )
( Groaning )
Bravo . Bravo , Susie .
( Pained gasping )
( Groans , gasping )
( Gasping weakly )
( Sobbing )
- ( Crunching ) - ( Screams )
( Breathing rhythmically )
( Agonized screaming )
( Gasping )
( Breathing rhythmically )
( Panting , whimpering )
( Screams , whimpers )
( Breathing rhythmically )
( Pained scream )
( Screams )
( Pained gasp )
( Breathing rhythmically )
- ( Crunching ) - ( Gasps )
( Panting )
- ( Coughing ) - ( Music stops )
( Wheezing )
( Breathing weakly )
( Whimpers )
( Panting , whimpering )
It 'll pass .
You 're not the first dancer who lost the room .
( Inhales deeply )
Susie : I 'm not usually dizzy .
An occasional collapse
is a vocational hazard , I 'm afraid .
I-I didn 't ... I didn 't collapse .
You 're on the floor , and that 's not where the dance ends .
( Panting )
I was trying not to throw up in your studio .
Susie , it 's fine .
It was wonderful .
Sara , can you take her to her room , please ?
You can rest for the rest of the day .
( Quiet chatter )
- How enlightening . - Woman : Okay , come on , girls .
- ( Clapping ) - Let 's go .
And one , and two , and three .
Blanc : And ...
( Clears throat )
( Trickling )
( Birds chirping )
( Panting )
Girl : No , Susie .
We have to study America .
I said no .
Woman : Susanna .
( Panting )
( Humming quietly )
♪ ♪
( Wheezing quietly )
( Wheezing )
( Inhales deeply )
( Groans quietly )
( Raspy groaning )
( Groaning )
( Raspy gasp )
( Grunts )
( Chuckles quietly )
- ( Grunts ) - ( Wheezing weakly )
( Clunking )
( Wheezing weakly )
You don 't look better .
Or are you this pale all the time ?
I will leave you .
Good night .
Susie : The Amish split
from the Mennonites in the 17th century .
They were worried the Mennonites
were becoming too liberal .
" They " ? Not " we " ?
You 've left religious thinking behind you , then ?
And you 're not comfortable talking about these things .
I don 't know why we are .
It 's difficult not to be curious about you .
In two days , you 've auditioned ,
been accepted and danced a lead .
How did your journey towards us begin ?
I went to New York .
To the Martha Graham center .
I saw you there three times .
I went once by bus ,
then I hitchhiked the other two .
That 's risky .
Were you punished ?
Yeah .
But I felt I had to see you .
What did it feel today
to dance volk in front of the one who made it ?
No , no . That 's a vain question .
Let me ask you another .
When you were dancing , what did it feel like ...
Inside you , inside your body ?
It felt like what I think it must feel like to fuck .
You mean to fuck a man " ?
No , I ...
Was thinking of an animal .
( Chuckles )
You looked ...
I 'm going to ask Caroline to work on your jumps with you .
Yours are nowhere near good enough yet .
We 'll have to build you up .
So that I can dance the protagonist
when you perform it ?
I 'll need to see you dance at this level time and time again .
I can do it .
Olga made volk seem like such heavy lifting .
( Water running )
She never understood the heart of volk .
- ( Water stops ) - ( Gasps quietly )
She lacked conviction .
I 'm relieved she 's gone .
Thank you for your help with that .
( Knocking )
( Door opens )
Susie ( chuckling ) : Madame Blanc ...
Wants me to dance the protagonist in volk .
I didn 't think it was gonna be like this .
She 's so kind . ( Chuckles )
That 's wonderful .
Are you all right ?
I 'm fine . I was just ...
I was just thinking about what Olga said in rehearsal .
About Patricia .
Susie ( in other room ) : What do you mean ?
Sara : She was active in some political groups .
No one knows where she is , really .
If she 's all right .
Was it true ...
What Olga said ?
Yes .
Patricia didn 't trust the matrons .
And I never understood why .
If I asked you for a favor tomorrow , would you do it ?
Yes .
- ( Grunts ) - We might get caught .
Okay .
( Heavy breathing )
( Heavy breathing continues )
( Wheezing )
Girl ( whispering ) : Mother . Mother .
Mother .
Mother . Mother . Mother . Mother .
Mother . Mother .
( Shuddering )
Woman ( whispering ) : Susanna .
( Girl screams )
- ( Heavy breathing ) - ( Dish clattering )
- ( Woman speaks German ) - ( Wheezing )
( Heavy breathing )
( Woman shouts in German )
( Gasping , shrieking )
( Dog barking in distance )
( Distant barking continues )
( Paper rustling )
( Sighs )
- Guten morgen . - Guten morgen .
Morgen .
Guten morgen .
Woman : Yeah , I know . It 's crazy .
Okay , well , let 's meet soon .
- ( Indistinct chatter ) - ( Chuckling )
Yeah , no , I 'm-I 'm ... I 'm ready .
I 'm almost out the door .
Okay . Yeah .
- I 'll see you soon . - Marketa .
- Marketa , come on . - I 'll see you soon .
Come on .
( Indistinct chatter )
( Whispers ) : Come , come , come .
( Door closes )
Are you sure no one 's coming ?
Oh , I 'm sure . Don 't worry .
Nobody comes here during the weekend .
( Laughing )
Patricia 's isn 't here .
Susie : Try looking for Olga 's .
Sara : Olga ...
She 's not here .
I just need a number .
For her parents or someone who can tell me for sure
she is or isn 't in Berlin .
Hmm . How odd .
( Rummaging )
( Distant laughter )
( Whispers ) : 1061 .
( Distant laughter continues )
1955 .
it 's bizarre .
( Woman humming quietly )
Woman : Here , kitty , kitty , kitty , kitty , kitty , kitty ...
( Laughter )
( Quiet , indistinct chatter )
( Laughter continues )
( Raucous laughter )
Here , kitty , kitty , kitty , kitty , kitty , kitty , kitty ...
( Laughter continues )
There 's nothing .
Come on .
- ( Door opens ) - ( Chuckles )
( Quiet chatter , laughter )
Woman : Sit down .
Blanc : This morning ,
we turn our instincts inward .
Miss Millius , miss Mandel ,
can you close the mirrors , please ?
Miss marks , no music .
I want to start work on a new piece .
A piece about rebirths .
The inevitable pull that they exert
and our efforts to escape them .
We 'll learn it now , but , Susie ,
you will improvise freely at its heart .
I 'm interested in your instincts here .
The piece will be called weider offnen .
Open again .
Allez .
( Breathing heavily )
- One , two , three , four . - ( Snapping fingers to beat )
One , two , three , four .
( Grunts , pants )
One ...
( Muffled ) : Two , three , four .
- One , two , three , four . - ( Raspy breathing )
One , two , three , four .
- ( Gasping ) - One , two , three , four .
One ...
( Raspy breathing )
( Panting )
Susie : Did something happen ?
- Hmm ? - To you , during it ?
N-no .
Did you ... did you ...
Did you feel something there ?
Someone ?
Or just something .
What made you say that ?
I don 't know .
- Am I confusing you ? - ( Chuckling )
No , it 's , um ...
It 's odd . It 's the ...
It 's the sort of thing Patricia would say .
It 's bizarre .
Come on .
Let 's get changed , or Sonia will leave without us .
I 've got a dress you can wear .
Double caposhi .
( Singing in German )
( Laughter , excited chatter )
♪ ♪
Woman : Susie !
( Indistinct chatter and laughter )
Oh , Susie !
( Panting )
( Shuddering breaths )
( Gasps softly )
( Object clatters )
( Distorted , echoing breaths )
( Pants , grunts )
( Gasping )
( Distorted voices )
( Gasps softly )
Sara ( whispers ) : Is it true ?
( Exhales )
( Screams )
- ( Panting , gasping ) - ( Screaming )
( Distorted , muffled chatter )
( Distorted shout )
( Distorted , gruff groan )
( Distorted screams and echoing voices )
( Panting )
( Wheezing )
Sara ( echoing ) : Is it true ?
( Indistinct whispering )
I know who I am !
( Dancers murmuring quietly )
- ( Gasps ) - It 's all right .
It 's okay .
Is she all right ?
It 's just a nightmare .
The Markos company special .
I 'm surprised it took this long .
Hey , let me know if she needs a valium .
( Groans )
( Laughter )
She 's right . I dreamt of hairballs in toilets
for three weeks before I got a decent night of sleep here .
Move over .
Susie : I 've only ever slept in bed with my sister .
Sara : We 're sisters now .
♪ ♪
( Bubbling )
( Teakettle whistling )
( Gasps quietly )
♪ ♪
Woman : Herr Klemperer ?
( Typewriter clacking and dinging )
Woman : And one , and two , and three .
And one , and two , and three .
One , and two , and three .
That 's-that 's okay .
( Indistinct conversations )
Do you want to do the jumps ?
Okay .
And ...
One , and two , and three .
And one , and two , and three .
No .
Elbows higher .
All right , one moment .
Susie , part of the jump is muscle ,
and that will develop as you condition ,
but you seem to have an aversion to them ,
and I don 't quite see why .
Are you so happy to be stuck to the earth ?
( Chuckles quietly )
There 's a yield before the push ,
which I don 't think you 're quite understanding .
Caroline . Could you come and do a series for us , please ?
Thank you .
And now you .
♪ ♪
( panting )
What I really want is to be on ...
On the floor right now , anyway .
( Chuckling ) : Well , of course .
That 's because you 're mistaking physical weakness
with artistic preference .
And because you 're tired .
- ( Chuckles ) - Susie : At this point ,
the jumps are opposing the pull of the structure ,
but ...
It 's soon for that , don 't you think ?
( Panting )
The floor work is ... is keeping the other dancers pushed down .
So this ...
This could echo that ...
( Panting )
On-on a slightly higher point of elevation .
If I stay close to the ground now
and go straight into the jumps where you have them later ,
then that 's more to the point .
The resistance is more ...
Emphatic .
Right ?
I don 't know how aware you are
of what times we lived through here 40 years ago .
Out of which this piece was made .
We learned at great cost through those years
the value of the balance of things .
Every arrow that flies feels the pull of the earth ,
but we must aim upwards .
We need to get you in the air .
( Quiet , indistinct chatter )
( Dancers gasping , murmuring )
Leave her , leave her , leave her , leave her , leave ...
( Choking , shuddering )
( Gasping )
( Sobbing )
Ja ?
( Chuckles softly )
Woman : She hit her head hard .
I heard it . I hope ...
I am ... I 'm looking for a dancer from your company .
Who are you looking for ?
You are Sara .
Yes .
May I help you ?
I am a friend from Patricia .
Sara : I don 't know what to make of any of this .
I know the kind of thing she was involved with ,
but I can 't see how any of this
could be happening inside the company .
Well , she describes ...
Something like a revolutionary organization
in a crisis of leadership .
With Markos very ill ...
I live there .
I have friends there .
I don 't see any evidence of this at all .
No one has ever approached me
or any of the other girls , as far as I know .
Read this .
What is this ?
This is Patricia 's diary .
Mother Markos .
Mother Meinhof .
The dance rehearsal .
Political action .
These two areas in Patricia 's life
were of equal importance .
This is how transference happens ,
how delusion is made .
Delusion , Sara ,
is a lie that tells a truth .
This says " witches . " " Mmm .
Maybe Patricia 's fantasies about witches ,
they are her way of processing some other form of intrigue .
The company 's a family .
There 's a lot of love there .
Love and manipulation ...
They ... they share houses very often .
They are frequent bedfellows .
Sorry , I don 't see this .
Eat .
( Dishes clattering nearby )
( Quiet chatter )
Only ...
Maybe the police , they missed something .
And Patricia , she did spoke of ...
Whole hidden areas of the building .
Actual rooms that are secret .
I don 't want to be disrespectful ...
I don 't ... but you 're asking me ,
- and I 'm telling you ... - Oh , please .
It 's a dance company .
We 're not talking about anything else .
Sara .
Please , only look closer .
Thank you for caring for Patricia ,
but I hope you don 't come again .
( Panting quietly )
( Door opens )
( Door closes )
- Good night . - Good night .
Woman : Sara , hurry up .
I 'm tired . I need the bathroom .
- Good night , doll . - Good night .
( Music playing , laughter in distance )
Woman : She hasn 't come back yet ?
- Maybe she 's seeing somebody . - ( Laughter )
( Indistinct chatter , laughter )
Blanc : Part of the issue always
is not being able to see your body in space .
One angle in one mirror or on film is not enough .
Movement is never mute .
It is a language .
It 's a series of energetic shapes ...
- ( Door opens ) - Written in the air
like words forming sentences .
Like poems .
Like prayers .
Spells ?
When you jump , it 's not the height
but the space beneath you that matters .
Every leap into the air must be a coup de foudre .
I don 't understand .
A strike of lightning .
A bolt of love , in fact .
That 's beautiful .
There are two things that dance can never be again :
Beautiful and cheerful .
Today , we need to break the nose
of every beautiful thing .
And if you 're going to be a dancer ,
you must learn French .
When you dance the dance of another ,
you make yourself in the image of its creator .
You empty yourself
so that her work can live within you .
Do you understand ?
Yeah .
You 're in a company now .
You have to find your right place .
You have to decide ...
What is it you want to be for this company ?
Is it the head ?
The spine ?
The sex " ?
The heart ?
The hands .
I want to be this company 's hands .
♪ ♪
- ( panting ) - Higher .
Higher . Higher .
- ( Panting continues ) - Higher .
Higher ! Higher .
- ( Grunting , panting ) - Higher .
Higher , higher , higher .
Higher .
Higher . Higher .
Higher . Higher . Higher .
Sometimes I only need to be told twice .
( Chuckles softly )
( All screaming )
( Frantic chatter in German )
( Distant clattering , footsteps )
( Distant footsteps , muffled chatter )
( Distant , muffled chatter )
( Footsteps )
( Whispering ) : 33 , 34 , 35 , 36 ,
37 , 38 , 39 ,
40 , 41 .
( Distant whimper )
57 , 58 , 59 ,
60 , 61 , 62 , 63 .
65 , 64 , 63 , 62 .
23 , 22 , 21 .
Ten , nine , eight ,
seven , six .
Two , one .
( Firm tap )
( Hollow thud )
( Clunking )
♪ ♪
( Rattling )
( Creaking )
♪ ♪
( Gasps softly )
( Quiet creaking )
( Shout , groan nearby )
( Yelling nearby )
- ( Chanting ) - Woman : Come with me ! Quickly !
( Screaming )
( Screaming continues , muffled )
- ( Door opens and closes ) - ( Rhythmic grunting )
( Grunting continues )
Klemperer : Patricia wrote about
" three mothers " lost in time ,
predating all Christian invention .
Pre-god . Pre-devil .
Mother Tenebrarum , mother Lachrymarum
and mother Suspiriorum .
Darkness , tears and sighs .
I saw images of that last night .
In porcelain , these very fine things .
You can tell they have money .
Patricia said that , uh , Markos
claims to be one of the three .
But there is dissent amongst them .
She wrote about " Markosites " and " Blancites . "
In-internal division .
Madame Blanc 's involved in this ?
Do they believe they 're witches ?
You can give someone your delusion , Sara .
That 's religion .
That was the reich .
The reich had these things .
Insignia .
Esoteric ritual .
These " mothers , " yeah , they could be
code names for founding members
with metaphoric histories .
I don 't know .
But I do know you are living with dangerous people .
- Patricia could still be in ... - ( Door closes )
In there .
( Grunts )
- They could be holding her . - ( Door opens and closes )
In the building .
Well , I cannot promise that the authorities
will come back to , uh , inspect a cabinet
full of porcelain after all that has happened .
But we can try .
And in the meantime , you must , uh , take care of yourself .
Perhaps you should leave .
You have somewhere you can go ?
I 'll figure it out .
And I think you should put this back .
Or better still , you leave it here .
Not good for them to know that you have it .
( Rattling )
♪ ♪
( Dogs barking , distant chatter )
( Whistles blowing in distance )
- ( Whistling ) - ( Shouting in German )
( Dog barking )
( Distant siren blaring )
( Quiet chatter )
( Speaking German )
( Takes deep breath )
( Door opens )
( Quiet , echoing wheezing )
( Wheezing continues )
Priest : Is anyone among you sick ?
Let him call for the elders of the church ;
and let them pray over him ,
anointing him with oil in the name of the lord .
And the prayer of faith shall save him that is sick ,
and the lord shall raise him up ;
and if he has committed sins ...
( Whispers ) : My daughter .
They shall be forgiven him .
My last one .
She 's my sin .
She 's what I smeared on the world .
( Wheezing )
( Crying )
You 're making some kind of deal with them .
I don 't know what you 're talking about .
( Sara gasping )
Sara : How can you know
what they 're going to ask you in return ?
Sara , whatever you have in your mind ,
- nothing is wrong . - ( Sara shudders )
You just haven 't seen the bill yet .
Nothing 's wrong .
♪ ♪
( Quiet , indistinct chatter )
What 's the matter with you ?
Huh ?
You don 't be so afraid about the white , Susie .
They need to see you from the very back row .
Where is Sara ?
She came early in the morning ,
did her makeup and left .
( Quiet chatter in German )
( Chorus vocalizing )
( Chorus singing in German )
( Quiet , indistinct chatter )
( Bell ringing )
Millius : Girls !
( Claps ) Vier minuten !
Four minutes !
- Vier minuten ! - ( Clapping )
Tak , tak .
( Quiet chatter continues )
( Door creaking open )
( Panting )
( Quiet chatter )
( Dancers whispering indistinctly )
Sara : Is it true ?
Patricia ( whispers ) : Sara .
Sara .
Patricia .
Patricia . Patricia .
- I knew it . - They 'll kill him .
I 'm sorry it took me so long .
I 'm so sorry .
What did they do to you ?
( Raspy ) : I wake up here every day .
It 's all over now . I 'll get you out .
The performance is starting upstairs .
Everyone will be looking the other way .
Get up . Get up .
Patricia !
- Patricia , get up . - I 'm trying .
Get up .
( Screams )
( Screams ) Get it off of me !
Sara !
- ( door slams shut ) - ( Running footsteps )
( Wheezing )
- ( Bell ringing ) - ( Quiet chatter )
( Ringing stops )
( Dancers whispering indistinctly )
( Chanting ) : Markos ! Markos ! Markos ! Markos !
( Quiet chatter )
( Whispers ) : Marketa .
Where is Sara ?
Sara " ?
I don 't know .
- Is she upstairs ? - No . I looked .
Tanner : just dance as if she 's with you .
( Grunting , panting )
( Wheezing nearby )
Patricia ( raspy ) : Sara !
( wheezing continues )
( Sara gasping )
Tanner ( whispers ) : Go !
( Speaking German )
( Gasping )
( Distant squealing )
( Panting )
( Shuddering breaths )
♪ ♪
( Rapid panting )
( Agonized screaming )
♪ ♪
( Grunting , gasping )
( Screams )
( Gasping )
( Rhythmic breathing )
( Grunts , exhales )
( Screaming )
( Whimpering )
( Agonized scream )
( Door opens )
No .
- No . - Sara , lie still .
- No ! ( Gasping ) - Sara .
Please . Please ...
( Screams )
No ! No !
♪ ♪
( Rhythmic breathing )
( Rhythmic breathing continues )
♪ ♪
( rhythmic grunting )
( Rhythmic breathing and grunting )
♪ ♪
( Rhythmic grunting )
( Rhythmic breathing continues )
( Panting )
( Rhythmic grunting )
( Screaming )
- ( Music stops ) - ( People gasping )
Sara !
( Sara panting , wheezing )
( Quiet chatter )
( Sara screaming )
( Speaks German )
( Wheezing , gasping )
( Chatter in German )
( Sara continues wheezing and gasping )
( Shuddering breaths )
- ( Sara moaning in pain ) - ( Chatter in German )
- ( Cracking ) - Good .
- ( Sara screams ) - Good . That 's good .
( Sara continues wheezing and gasping )
( Gasping quietly )
♪ ♪
- ( gasps ) - ( Wind whistling )
( Voices screaming , whispering indistinctly )
( Screaming and whispering stop )
( Door opens )
Susie ( telepathically ) : I 'm sorry I went off book .
Blanc ( telepathically ) : This can 't happen again .
You 're only just starting to understand , Susie .
We brought Sara back upstairs
to try to complete the performance in time ,
but then you derailed it .
Susie : Did I hurt those people ?
Blanc : Not this time .
They saw a dance .
That 's all .
Susie : It 's all a mess , isn 't it ?
The one out there .
( Spoken aloud ) : The one in here .
The one that 's coming .
Why is everyone
so ready to think the worst is over ?
( Telepathically ) : I could explain everything to you .
I think it would be wrong , though .
( Gasps quietly )
♪ ♪
One , two , three , four .
- One , two , three , four . - ( Panting )
- One , two , three , four . - ♪ Open again ♪
one , two , three , four .
One , two , three , four .
♪ We breathe again ♪
♪ upon the other shore ♪
♪ washed out ♪
♪ we live again ♪
♪ we 're demons , all of us ♪
♪ we 're open ♪
♪ just say it ♪
♪ just say the magic words . ♪
♪ ♪
Herr doktor .
( Laughter , indistinct chatter )
( Cheering , applause , indistinct chatter )
( Speaking French )
( Panting )
( Grunting )
♪ ♪
( grunts )
( Quiet , indistinct chatter )
( Waiter speaking French )
( Song playing in French )
( Festive shouting , laughter )
( Festive chatter )
( Song continues playing in French )
( Panting quietly )
♪ ♪
( Chuckling )
( Anke whimpers )
♪ ♪
( Laughter )
( Singing in German )
( Singing continues )
( Laughter )
( Singing and laughter fade )
♪ ♪
( panting quietly )
( Gasping )
( Shrieking )
( Growling , shrieking )
( Shrieking laughter )
( Echoing footsteps )
( Distorted , distant screams )
♪ ♪
( Heavy breathing )
( Distorted , distant screams continue )
♪ ♪
( Rhythmic breathing )
( Wheezing , rhythmic breathing )
( Whimpering )
( Sobbing , moaning )
( Gasping )
( Pained whimpering )
( Rhythmic breathing continues )
( Klemperer whimpering )
( Intense , rhythmic breathing and moaning )
( Cackling )
( Rhythmic breathing continues )
( Choral singing )
( Sobbing )
You look afraid .
( Laughs )
She 's afraid for you .
( Rhythmic breathing and grunting )
( Choral singing continues )
( Hissing , chattering )
( Straining , raspy ) : There will be nothing of you
left inside .
Only space for me .
I came here for this .
( Rhythmic grunting and breathing continue )
You 've all waited long enough .
Ah !
It is happening .
It is happening !
( Cackling )
( Choral singing continues )
( Rhythmic grunting and moaning continue )
( Shrieks )
Do you come here willingly ?
Hmm ?
Huh ?
You must have no doubts , Susie .
If you do , I can take you back .
I can take all of this from your head .
You can forget everything .
( Wheezing laughter )
I want this to be pure .
( Straining , raspy ) : We all know what you want .
( Straining grunt )
This isn 't vanity .
This isn 't ...
Art !
There is something wrong here .
Can you not feel it ?
This is not right .
We have to stop this now .
We have been on
two sides of this
for too long now .
Matrons ( chanting ) : Markos ! Markos ! Markos !
Markos ! Markos ! Markos ! Markos !
Markos ! Markos ! Markos !
- Markos ! Markos ! - ( Shrieking )
Markos ! Markos !
( Squishing , crunching )
( Wheezing )
( Deep , gasping breaths )
If you accept me ,
you must put down the woman who bore you .
Think of that false mother now .
( Labored breathing )
- ( Wheezing ) - Markos : Reject her .
Expel her .
You have the only mother you need here .
Death to any other mother .
Say it .
( Screams )
Death to any other mother .
( Matrons shrieking )
( Whimpering )
( Shrieking continues )
( Taking deep breaths )
Who are you ?
For whom were you anointed ?
Which of the three mothers ?
Mother ...
( Wheezing , whimpering )
Mother Suspiriorum .
I am she .
( Wheezing , whimpering )
( Gasping )
( Choking , gasping )
( Matrons shrieking )
( Deep growl )
( Shrieking continues )
Markos .
( Crunching , squishing )
( Shrieking continues )
Markos !
( Panting )
( Shrieking )
( Moans softly )
( Groaning )
( Sobbing )
( Gasping , sobbing )
( Panting )
Markos !
Markos .
( Panting )
( Echoing ) : Death to any other mother .
Markos .
♪ ♪
Markos !
♪ Come under my wings ♪
♪ little bird ♪
♪ come under ♪
Markos !
♪ My wings ♪
♪ little bird ♪
♪ come under my wings ... ♪
Markos !
♪ Unmade ♪
♪ unmade ♪
♪ I swear that there 's nothing ♪
♪ up my sleeve ♪
( distorted voices hissing and screaming )
♪ bring it back again ♪
( voices growing louder )
♪ I swear there 's nothing ... ♪
( whispering ) : I am the mother .
( Distorted voices screaming and groaning )
♪ ♪
What do you ask ?
To die .
♪ Broken pieces ♪
Patricia : Mother .
Mother , we 're so tired .
♪ Unmade ♪
( sobbing , moaning )
What do you ask ?
To die .
I want to die .
♪ I swear there 's nothing ... ♪
sweet girl .
What do you ask ?
Die .
♪ Come under my wings ♪
♪ come under my wings ♪
- ♪ under my wings . ♪ - Susie : Yes .
Dance . Dance .
Keep dancing .
It 's beautiful .
( Echoing deep breaths )
( Echoing gasps )
( Gasping )
( Quiet chatter in German )
Yeah . Okay .
Good . Good .
( Sighs )
( Singing in German )
( Gasping , panting )
( Grunting )
( Panting )
( Gasping , whimpering )
( Frightened moaning )
( Whimpering )
( Birds cawing )
( Panting )
- ( Yawns ) - My god , what a night .
I definitely drank too much wine .
( Speaking French )
- Bonjour . - Bonjour .
( Chatter continues in French )
- Guten morgen . - Morning .
Good morning .
- ( Grunting ) - ( Humming a tune )
( Whimpering )
( Gasping weakly )
( Gasps , grunts )
( Quiet chatter in distance )
( Quiet , shuddering breaths )
♪ ♪
( door opens )
I regret what my daughters did to you .
I wasn 't in a position to prevent it .
I believe you deserve to know the truth .
Your wife did try to make it south
to Teplice .
She was apprehended by border guards
in the woods just outside of Glashutte .
She was then taken to Theresienstadt camp .
She lived there for 20 days .
On the 11th of November , 1943 ,
the commandant of the camp , a man named Burger ...
Ordered all 40,000 detained there
stand outside in the cold for a census .
Hours and hours passed .
Some hundreds died of exposure .
Your wife had two women with her as she died .
Women she had befriended ,
who made her feel that she was not alone .
Her final thoughts ...
Were of a birthday
when you took her to a concert as a surprise .
Chopin and Brahms .
( Whimpering , sobbing )
It was the first time you held her hand .
She was cold when she died .
But she wasn 't afraid .
She was thinking only of you .
( Klemperer sobbing softly )
Of Anke Meier ...
Of Patricia Hingle ...
Of Sara Simms ...
Of Susanna Bannion ,
of all the women of your undoing ...
Every memory will vanish .
They will melt away in the sun
and be gone .
( Gasping , choking )
( Dish shatters )
- Herr doktor . - ( Gasping continues )
Herr doktor .
( Shuddering )
( Taking deep breaths )
( Train approaching )
( Humming a tune )
( Quiet , indistinct chatter )
( Speaking German )
( Young girl singing in German )
( Chatter continues in German )
♪ ♪
♪ This is what I was thinking ♪
♪ about our bodies ♪
♪ what they mean ♪
♪ for our salvation ♪
♪ only the clothes that ♪
♪ we standup in ♪
♪ just the ground ♪
♪ on which we stand ♪
♪ is the darkness ♪
♪ ours to take ? ♪
♪ Bathed in lightning ♪
♪ bathed in heat ♪
♪ all is well ♪
♪ as long as we keep spinning ♪
♪ here now ♪
♪ dancing behind the wall ♪
♪ hear the old songs ♪
♪ and laughter within ♪
♪ all forgiven ♪
♪ always or never be true ♪
♪ when I arrive , will ♪
♪ you come and find me ? ♪
♪ in a crowd ♪
♪ be one of them ♪
♪ mother wants us ♪
♪ right beside her ♪
♪ no tomorrows ♪
♪ at peace . ♪
♪ ♪
( Music fades )